<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A handkercher for parents wet eyes vpon the death of children. A consolatory letter to a friend.</title>
            <author>I. C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17458</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120682</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855876</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855876</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21384</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17458)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21384)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1059:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A handkercher for parents wet eyes vpon the death of children. A consolatory letter to a friend.</title>
                  <author>I. C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 67, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E[liz.] A[llde] for Michael Sparkes, dwelling at the blue Bible in Greene Arbour,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: I.C.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Children --  Death --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21384:1"/>
            <p>A HANDKERCHER FOR PARENTS WET EYES, VPON THE DEATH OF CHILDREN.</p>
            <p>A Conſolatory Letter to a Friend.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. A.</hi> for <hi>Michael Sparkes,</hi> dwelling at the blue Bible in Greene Arbour. 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21384:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <figure/>
               <pb facs="tcp:21384:2"/>
To the Reader that is, or may be exerciſed with this kinde of Croſſe.</head>
            <p>GEntle Reader, I did not thinke that euer any <hi>Lines</hi> of mine ſhould haue lookt in at a <hi>Printing-houſe.</hi> My <hi>Conceit</hi> is not wont to be in the <hi>Eaning Moode,</hi> as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that with <hi>Iacobs</hi> Ewes, it ſhould bring forth but <hi>ſpotted</hi> and <hi>ſtraked Lambes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet now at the inſtance of a <hi>Payre</hi> of worthy <hi>Friends,</hi> that had equally drunke of this <hi>Cup of Sorrow,</hi> I haue yeelded to put the <hi>Preſſe</hi> to a ſhort <hi>affliction;</hi> and to communicate to <hi>All,</hi> what was firſt intended for the comfort of <hi>One.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I might haue ſate ſtill, <hi>with the finger on the lip,</hi> amidst thoſe ſage and faithfull <hi>Counſellors</hi> and <hi>Companions</hi> (Good Bookes) or <hi>haue ſung to my ſelfe, and the</hi> Muſes <hi>onely;</hi> or to a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne Friend, or Two, with whom euery Thing ſhould haue receiu'd a fauourable interpretation: But for thy ſake, that I might not bee <hi>vncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21384:3"/>
I am faine to be <hi>imprudent,</hi> in aduenturing to trench thus neere vpon the Worlds <hi>tuchy Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I may hap by this meanes, to bee carried ſhortly into the <hi>Street,</hi> where they ſell <hi>Frankincenſe,</hi> and <hi>Sweet Pouders,</hi> and <hi>Pepper,</hi> and ſuch Things as they vſe to cloathe in <hi>weake</hi> and <hi>worthleſſe Papers.</hi> No matter. It was not to my <hi>Pen</hi> any <hi>Herculean Labour;</hi> nor to <hi>My ſelfe</hi> in the writing altogether <hi>ingratefull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if in the <hi>vaſt Petegrination</hi> of <hi>Books,</hi> it may pleaſe God, that but one <hi>delected heart</hi> may by any good word in It, be a little lifted vp; or <hi>Paſſion</hi> haſht, and calmed; or <hi>flowing Eye</hi> dryed; or <hi>ſorrow</hi> made happy, by being tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to a righter <hi>Obiect;</hi> or any (yet entirely enioying the faire <hi>Bleſſings</hi> of <hi>Marriage</hi>) fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed againſt a future ſtorme, if God ſee good to ſend it; I ſhall hold my ſelfe abundantly rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from Heauen in that one <hi>Booke,</hi> or <hi>Page,</hi> or <hi>Paſſage,</hi> or <hi>Line,</hi> though all the reſt of theſe <hi>Leaues</hi> periſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> haue onely <hi>dipt the Tip of my finger</hi> in Comfort for thee; The God of all <hi>Conſolation</hi> can giue thee the fulneſſe of it; which is His wiſh to Thee, that wiſheth Ill to None.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21384:3"/>
            <head>To my worthy Friend Maſter <hi>I. R.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, I know you doe now feele what it is to bee a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to barre you altogether from lamenting &amp; ſorrowing in ſuch an Accident as this <hi>[The death of your belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Sonne]</hi> were as vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as to chide a <hi>Man,</hi> for ſhewing himſelfe ſenſible, when a Tooth is drawne, or a Leg or an Arme is ſawd off from his body. For if I ſhould perſwade you that theſe may
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21384:4"/>
bee taken from you without feeling, or paine, you would ſay, I plaid the <hi>Mountebanke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For mine owne part, I was at the firſt vnlookt for word of <hi>[Dead]</hi> like <hi>Niobe, Lapideus factus,</hi> Cold at the heart; and hauing recollected my ſelfe, found I was a ſharer in your loſſe, and could not temper mine Eyes from running ouer as for a Kinſman of mine own. (For why ſhould not I haue an intereſt, nay a kind of affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity with <hi>His Sonne,</hi> who vouchſafed to bee ſo kind a nouriſher of <hi>My Daughter?</hi>)</p>
            <p>Had you loſt him new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, and but ſaluting the world;
<q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Junent. Sat. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note>—Primes incipientem</l>
                  <l>Edere vagitus, &amp; adhuc à matre rubentem;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21384:4"/>Firſt ſquayling Cryes from In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Throte outſtrayning,</l>
                  <l>And from his Mother, yet the Redde retayning;</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Or a Youngling firſt beſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his Hobby-horſe, or driuing his Top, or new lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the way to <hi>Schoole;</hi> the parting had not beene ſo bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. We doe ſomewhat eaſily ſhake hands with greene and ſlight Acquaintances.</p>
            <p>But he was <hi>Solidus Adoleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens, A growne Man,</hi> arriued halfe way to the <hi>Solſlice of his Age; Strong, actiue, well ſhaped, well-graced, faire-demeanord, ſtudious,</hi> of an honeſt and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous diſpoſition, yeelding not onely the bloſſomes, but the fruits of a good education.</p>
            <p>Graue, with the firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing <hi>Downe vpon his Chinne,</hi> yet without any grumneſſe or
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21384:5"/>
ſowreneſſe of manners.</p>
            <p>His by-ſtudies and delights manly and generous, ſeruing either to enable him for the ſeruice of his Prince &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; As the exerciſe of <hi>Ames</hi> and <hi>Hardiment.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Hor. ad Lol. Epiſt. <hi>19. l. 1.</hi>
                  </note>— Adde virilia, quod ſpecioſius Arma,</l>
               <l>Non eſt qui tractet.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His manly Armes none beares with better grace.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Or by imparting their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to others, to make the Vſer thereof welcome. As Muſicke, Dancing, Hiſtory, Faire-writing, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To his God he was religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and deuout, early remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring his Creator, wearing the Threſhold of his Houſe, &amp; ſitting attentiue at the feete of this Miniſters.</p>
            <p>To his Father and Mother
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21384:5"/>
obſeruant and dutifull; To his Kinred louing; To his Elders reuerent; To his Equals facile and ſociable; To All courteous and pleaſing; Which turnd Mens eyes and regards vpon him, and made him accepted and deſired, both of one and other.</p>
            <p>And for the maine Studie, whereunto hee had addicted himſelfe, he was by your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct &amp; trayning ſo good a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient therein, for notion and vnderſtanding of the paſſages, if not for dexterity of Acting (which is acquired by Time and vſe) that he was in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner fitted and prepared to haue put his ſhoulders vnder your burthen, and by inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at once both your place and toyles, to haue giuen your yeeres at length their deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21384:6"/>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>acation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 14.</note>
               <hi>But Man that is borne of a Woman, hath but a ſhort time to liue. He commeth vp like a Flower, and is cropt off. He is pluckt from the Stalke as an unripe Grape; and ſhaken downe as the winde ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth downe the Oliue bloſſomes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know, you are not Stoicall, without affections;
<q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Perſ.</note>—<hi>Ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> enum tibi cornea fibra eſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Your heart-ſtrings are not ſo tough and horny.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onos vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os facile ſolui in Iachrymas.</note>I haue noted your eyes ſometimes to ſtand great with teares at others woes,<note n="*" place="margin">Chancer.</note> 
               <hi>for pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty renneth ſoone in Gentle heart.</hi> And therefore I blame you not to melt, yea, to ake, and be ſore of ſuch a wound and mayme as this. This is not a ſlea-bite, or a ſcratch with a pinne; nor a forraigne hurt a great way diſtant, but <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtike</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21384:6"/>
and <hi>Concerning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>David</hi> thought his ſorrow iuſtifiable for his Sonne that was a <hi>Rebell,</hi> and almoſt a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricide;</hi> your ſorrow cannot but be iuſt for ſo towardly, ſo deare, ſo precious a Sonne: A right <hi>Beniamin,</hi> the Sonne of your Right hand, the Staffe and Prop of your old Age.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aegritudinem dolorem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi moderatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> improbari non opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet.</hi> One muſt not be ſhent for moderate ſorrow and <hi>griefe of minde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet you muſt take heed of making your Griefe vniuſt, by exceeding a iuſt and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar meaſure in it. As we muſt not be <hi>doloris expertes,</hi> indolent and void of <hi>ſorrow,</hi> for that's <hi>inhumane:</hi> So neither may we be <hi>perditè dolentes,</hi> immea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable, obſtinate, deſperate
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21384:7"/>
grieuers, for that's <hi>vn-chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Strangulat incluſus dolor at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or aeſtuat intus, Cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur &amp; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicare ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note>It muſt not be ſtopt too ſoone; for then the <hi>Teares turne backe to drowne the heart. Iobs</hi> Friends ſaid not a word to him for the firſt ſeuen daies, but let paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue his courſe, and tire it ſelfe, themſelues ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſad and ſilent by him.</p>
            <p>But on the other ſide, you muſt not ſtay it too long; for then it playes the Tyrant, and killes and ſlayes without mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>Worldly ſorrow cauſeth death</hi> and diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>It's like a foraigne power call'd in, to the Ayde of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Kingdome, which cannot be got out againe, but proues a worſe enemy then that it came to expell.</p>
            <p>You haue already plaid the part of a louing Father, wept
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21384:7"/>
the Teares of Nature; you muſt now change your Copy, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw your finger from the ſore, and play the part of a wiſe and conſtant man: And that is, either to preuent a miſchiefe when it is approch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; or if it happen, to amend it, and labour to make it as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle as may be: According to the old precept, <hi>Bona quàm maxima facere, mala contrahere atque imminuere.</hi> Extend and inlarge any Good to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt,<note place="margin">Hebetant Rationis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ciem mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeriae. Omnes in monendo ſapientes ſumus, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aure ipſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> liqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mus, no in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>telligimu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Eru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mid</hi>
               </note> but contract and dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh (what you can) the euill.</p>
            <p>But becauſe generally all ſuccours faile vs in aduerſity; paſſion ſending vp ſuch Fogs, that the vnderſtanding is blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, (though we haue beene (in our owne wel-faring) ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo able, to miniſter words of comfort to others in <hi>their</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:21384:8"/>
diſtreſſes) giue me leaue at this Time, to take you by the hand, and onely to ſet you in the way to the doore of <hi>Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Multa etiam ab Olitore, recte atque in loco proferri poſſunt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Eu'n an Herb-wife ſometimes may</l>
               <l>Things right, and to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſay.</l>
            </q>
            <div type="part">
               <head>CONSIDERATION. I.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, call to your remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance that great Statute, <hi>That all muſt once dye.</hi> And that doome for ſinne,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.27 Gen. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Duſt thou art, and into Duſt thou ſhalt returne.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Herod.</note>
                     <hi>Omnibus vna manet nox,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fit calcanda ſemel via lethi.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>One darkſome night awaits
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21384:8"/>
each liuing wight,</l>
                  <l>And Deaths high-way muſt once be trod (deſpight.)</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Naſcimur, &amp; morimur,</hi> is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ones Motto; <hi>Wee are all borne mortall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What maruell to ſee that cut aſunder which may bee cut aſunder? That melted which is fuſible and apt to melt? That burnt which is combuſtible? The Sonne die as well as the Father, being borne vnder the ſame Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Mortality, that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was?</p>
               <p>All vnions in this world muſt be diſſolued: Fathers and Children muſt bee ſeuered; Friends &amp; Friends, Husbands &amp; Wiues, as they had a <hi>Time</hi> to come together, ſo they muſt haue a <hi>Time</hi> to part aſunder.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sic Natura poſtulat, nec graue
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21384:9"/>
putandum, fieri quod neceſſe eſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So Nature craues, nor thinke it much to ſee,</l>
                  <l>The Thing ſo done, that needs ſo done muſt be.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>CONSIDERATION. 2.</head>
               <p>SEcondly, conſider that it is the caſe of others with you. If you had beene the firſt, or onely Father that had loſt a Sonne, and no other had drunk of this <hi>Cup</hi> before you; then you had ſome Colour to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, and to continue and ſpin out your laments. <hi>But the worme is spred euen vnder Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Branches; Kings and Princes are depriued of their Children,</hi> as well as meaner men; yea thoſe <hi>Children, that ſhould keepe their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21384:9"/>
Kingdome from ſtaggering.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hiſtories are full of inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; Whence you (that are ſo conuerſant in thoſe readings) can eaſily ſtore your ſelfe; let it bee inough for me to reach you onely three or foure fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Ones, within the reach &amp; l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en of our owne memory.</p>
               <p>That Noble Lord of the North loſt three of his Sonnes, <hi>In florentiſſima aetate,</hi> in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bloome of youth, and luſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: One, before his aged Eyes, by the ruggedneſſe of an vnbroken Horſe; and Two together out of a Boate paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ouer a rough Ferry.</p>
               <p>You know, but a little ſince, A worthy Knight of our Country loſt one of his Sons, a luſty yong Gentleman, in our owne Riuer, his Horſe leaping with his Rider, plum ouer the Boates ſide.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:21384:10"/>A Noble Gentlewoman, our neighbour, after the loſſe of a deare and excellent Husband, loſt in the Circle of a few yeeres, ſixe of her Children, all growne Men and Women, three faire Daughters, and three braue Sonnes; the yong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in a Tempeſt of Bullets, at the aſſault of an vnfortunate Iland.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Prince Palatines</hi> loſſe of his Firſt-borne Sonne, by the vnlucky running of a Ship with full ſaile ouer his Barge, is freſh in all minds.</p>
               <p>Periſhing by misfortune is a greater <hi>Cut,</hi> then leauing the world by Gods Viſitation. So that your caſe being common with others, and more eaſie then diuers others, That may ſtifle ſome ſighs, and calme a many repining complaints.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:21384:10"/>
                  <hi>Inter arma &amp; lituos,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Am. Mar. lib.</hi> 26. c. 13.</note> conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis <hi>aequatio leuiorafacit pericula.</hi> Euen among weapons and ſounding Trumpets, the equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Condition makes the danger lighter, and leſſe ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>Who reckes his life, or dreads death, when in the whirle and Din of warre, hee ſeeth not onely his fellow-Soldiers knockt downe beſide him, but a many valiant yong Nobles, reſolute and hardy Knights, and Commanders, that erewhile cleft the crowdes, and hewed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues a way thorow the thickeſt Rankes of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, fallen to ground alſo, and lying breathles among Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of other dead bodies?</p>
               <p>What a <hi>Rowe</hi> might bee preſented of weeping Fathers
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21384:11"/>
and Mothers for their Sonnes, accompliſht (at their no ſmall charge) with learning and breeding, ſodainely hurried out of the world vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Sword or Rapiers point, in deſperate quarrels, or Challenges and Duells, within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of halfe Your Time?</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Age, deſine; intuonſque aliorum miſerias,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tua lenius feres.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Goe to, giue ouer, and by view</l>
                  <l>Of others Griefes, your owne ſubdue.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>CONSIDERATION. 3.</head>
               <p>THirdly, the impoſſibility of recouering your loſſe.<note place="margin">Prorſus nö ſunt tentä<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilia. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pho.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <q>Optimum eſt obliuiſci, quodrecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perari non poteſt.</q>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21384:11"/>The beſt ſalue for an irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerable loſſe, is <hi>Obliuion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non placet iſtud factum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Terent. Adelph. Act.</hi> 4.5.8</note> 
                  <hi>ſi poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem mutare; nunc cum non queo, aequo animo fero.</hi> This fact likes me not, if I knew how to help it; now that I cannot, what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy but <hi>patience?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If your Sonne were to bee bought and brought to life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine at a ſet price of ſorrow, I beleeue, you would bid frankly for him. But, <hi>The Graue returnes no Men. You ſhall goe to him, he ſhall not come againe to you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore to ſit day by day with folded armes, and dropping eyes, &amp; a heart heauy as lead, for the Loſſe cannot poſſibly be regayned; as it is vnprofitable to the bemoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſo 'tis a hurt to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moaner; yea of one harme to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21384:12"/>
make Two. Nay it is to reſiſt the high and heauenly Will, and to bee found Striuers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God: In which number, I know, you would be loth to be ranked. <hi>You haue not ſo lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>CONSIDERATION. 4.</head>
               <p>FOurthly, Time it ſelfe may miniſter ſome Phyſicke to your Affliction. A Priſoners Irons ſeeme not ſo heauy to him the ſecond day, as the firſt. No griefe hath ſo much violence in the continuation, as in the firſt Acceſſe.</p>
               <p>Take the ſimpleſt <hi>Country-Mother,</hi> the weakeſt <hi>Nurſe of a Village,</hi> that wrings her hands, and teares her haire, &amp;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21384:12"/>
laues the Ground (on which ſhe wallowes) with eye-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and takes on neuer ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potently for her departed Child; and the ſpace of a few dayes will ſlake the rage of her ſorrow, and anon bury it in vtter forgetfulneſſe.</p>
               <p>That which <hi>Time</hi> worketh in the ignorant, ſhall not <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> together effect as eaſily in the wiſe?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>CONSIDERATION 5.</head>
               <p>Fiftly, But you will ſay, your Son might haue liu'd lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. And hee might as well haue dyed ſooner. Who can ſhew me a Leaſe of his life vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Seale for one houre? Why may not euery day proue our laſt day?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:21384:13"/>Some are ſuffocated in the wombe; others crowz'd to death in the Birth. One is ſnatcht away in the Cradle: Another mow'd off in his <hi>May</hi> of youth; being onely ſhewne to the world like a curious picture finiſht, and ſtraight the Curtaine drawne and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mou'd away againe. Its the priuiledge but of few, to ſtep down vpon the Griece of Old Age. Our life, from the firſt houre to the laſt, gallops on towards death: And who ſeeth not, with what ſpeed it conquers euen the longeſt way in this iourney?</p>
               <p>If Time then be the thing you ſtand on for your Sonne, how ſmall a matter of Oddes is a little more or leſſe Time in ſo fugitiue and ſwift a <hi>Race?</hi> It's ſcarce diſcernable.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:21384:13"/>A Cart full of Priſoners are brought to execution; what skills it which is firſt, or third, or ſixt, or tenth, or ſixteenth? All muſt dye. What gets hee that is delayed till the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, aboue him that was executed in the morning? Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps to be ſuperafflicted with longer expectance and pre-ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion; ſighing that his turne had not beene with the formoſt.</p>
               <p>(But the Priſoner may not appoint his owne courſe, that is in the Iudge or the Sheriffe to diſpoſe of.)</p>
               <p>The whole world is but a Cart of condemned perſons: God culls out euery day ſome and ſome for Execution.</p>
               <p>This very Minute a Slaue dyes, foredone with toyle and hardſhip. Inſtantly, a King or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21384:14"/>
great Lord mounts the Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. By and by a Mechanick, a Ruſticke, a Peſant, a Milk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid, a Cow-heard, a Schoole-boy, or Girle, ſuffer.</p>
               <p>Straight after, a Royall Lady or Princeſſe ſtoopes her faire Neck to the Blocke.</p>
               <p>Anon, a freſh, louely, actiue, vigorous Youth, a beauteous young Damſell (Ornaments to the world) are preſented to the Axe.</p>
               <p>Behold now, a feeble old man is led vp, hauing ſcarce life inough left, to be kild, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The oldeſt of theſe hath not liu'd a minute ouer his Time, nor the youngeſt a minute vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: for neither might the one budge any ſooner without <hi>ſummons &amp; order;</hi> nor the other tarry any longer, being call'd away. But you will ſay, He
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21384:14"/>
had no cauſe to complaine, that was reſpited to <hi>Old Age,</hi> which brings with it a ſaciety of liuing. Nor You, by the ſame reaſon. For when God hath decreed, I ſhall liue no longer, This (fall it when it will) is my <hi>Old Age.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee are not Caruers of our owne Times. Hee onely that predeſtinated the houre of our Birth from all Eternity, hath power to decree the houre of our Death.</p>
               <p>You neither could cauſe your Child to bee borne ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or to dye later. Times Maker knowes the fitteſt Times for all his purpoſes.</p>
               <p>He hath not appointed all to liue the ſame terme of yeeres. Some goe before,<note place="margin">Serius aut citius, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam prope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus ad vnam. <hi>Ouid.</hi>
                  </note> ſome after. But firſt or laſt, all arriue at the ſame marke.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21384:15"/>The Husbandman reapes not all his Akers at once, but one ſooner, another later, as they are ſooner or later ripe. Let God alone, hee knowes (better then any Farmer) the number and condition of his Akers, &amp; where he findes one forward, turn'd white betimes, (though but the other day greene, and in the blade) there he puts in his Sickle, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries it into the Heauenly Barne: <hi>A Place of ſafety.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which with longer ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding might haue ſpilt &amp; ſhed, or beene wanſled, and come to nothing.</p>
               <p>Long laſting, euen to the froſtieſt old Age is not the matter,<note place="margin">Puer cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. <hi>Eſa. 65.</hi>
                  </note> for there may bee a Child of a hundred yeeres old, that yet is not ready for Heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:21384:15"/>God hath reſerued to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe alone, the ſight of the run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out of the Glaſſe. <hi>Man knoweth not his Time and End:</hi> but vnperceiuingly ſlides into it, <hi>as the Fiſh into the Net, or the Bird into the Snare,</hi> God puſhing on meanes, to vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreamt of, and vnſuſpected, to ſerue his Decree.</p>
               <p>It is with men in the world, as with the Veſſels in a Potters Shop. There are of all ſorts, ſizes, and faſhions. That which to day is whole, &amp; handſome, and vſefull: to morrow, with a knocke, or a fall, may bee broken to ſheards. Your Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell was ſheene and new, of a firme making, likely to haue laſted many a faire yeere, euen till it had flawed and mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred away of it ſelfe; but it ſtood in harmes-way, diſeaſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21384:16"/>
and ſickneſſe gaue it a knocke, and a cracke, which could not bee ſoldred. And indeed, the ſleekeſt, the ſweeteſt, the trim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt <hi>Diſh of China,</hi> is but a <hi>China Diſh;</hi> handle it, or ſet it vp as charily as you can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe.</p>
               <p>Wee would haue our Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle burne downe into the ſoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket; but God hath a wind to blow it out, ſometimes as ſoone as lighted; or a Thiefe to conſume it with guttering, ere any Eye heed it. Few of our liuing Candles (not one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt a Thouſand) laſt bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the laſt Inch.</p>
               <p>Hee that numbreth all our Times and houres, hath num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred your Sonnes alſo, and ſet him his day, beyond which he could not paſſe.</p>
               <p>Honour him with free
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21384:16"/>
yeelding this preeminence to him, and let it ſtop your mouth, and ſtoope your heart. <hi>I held my peace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 1. Sam. Iob.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe thou didst it. It is the Lord, let him doe whatſoeuer he pleaſeth. He giueth, he taketh, bleſſed be the Name of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But he doth nothing but for the beſt to them that loue him. Many times Life is not ſo much taken away, as Death giuen for a ſpeciall Fauour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iuſt and Mercifull men are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from the Euils to come.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay.</note> How many times ouer, haue ſome dyed, by liuing long?</p>
               <p>Righteous <hi>Abel,</hi> the ſecond Sonne of the ſole Emperour of the whole Earth, was cut off in his <hi>Youth.</hi> The Eternall Son of God himſelfe died a young Man.</p>
               <p>Our Eſtimate of Life is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21384:17"/>
wrong, and falſe; quite odde and different from Gods. We meaſure it like <hi>Canuas,</hi> by the <hi>Ell;</hi> God like <hi>Gold,</hi> by the <hi>Graine.</hi> Our Examen is by the <hi>Tale,</hi> ſo many <hi>Scores;</hi> Gods by the <hi>Touch,</hi> ſo vertuous, ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary, of ſuch an <hi>Allay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, God hauing thus qualified Your Sonne with Grace, made him early ready for Heauen; hee had attain'd his due, and true Seniority, and could not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine that hee lackt Time, or had liu'd too little while.</p>
               <q>
                  <note place="margin">M. B. Hol. <hi>in Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat. of</hi> Perſ.</note>Action, not Time, does number Age.</q>
               <p>The Heathens haue noted it for a bleſſing, to dye young.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>nd.</note>
                     <hi>Aetate prima moritur, quem diy diligunt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:21384:17"/>Early to dye it him behoou'd,</l>
                  <l>Whom gods aboue ſo dearely lou'd. <hi>And againe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>—<hi>Nec illi,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quem Diuum Pater atque homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, quem Phoebus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Amabat ante omnes, ſera licuit gaudere ſenecta.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor might he (here) liue to be old as other,</l>
                  <l>Whom <hi>Ioue</hi> and <hi>Phoebus</hi> ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred as their brother.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cleobis</hi> and <hi>Biton,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cic. Tuſc, quaſt.</note> when their Mother for their piety in drawing her Chariot to the Temple themſelues, (in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Horſes) prayed, that they might be rewarded with the greateſt bleſſing that could poſſibly happen from God to Man; were both found dead next morning in their ſleepe.</p>
               <p>And when newes hereof
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21384:18"/>
was brought to their Mother, as of a great misfortune: <hi>No</hi> (ſaith ſhe) <hi>I will neuer count my ſelfe vnfortunate, that was the Mother of ſuch Sonnes, as the gods haue guerdon'd with immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality for their pious Act.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Shall a Pagan Mother, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no other light but that of <hi>duske nature,</hi> count it for a <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Fauour,</hi> that her excellent Sonnes haue early quit this life and world; and a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Father inlightned with the Raies of the <hi>Sacred Truth breathed from the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> pule, and repine, and looke ſowre vpon Heauen, and God, when in mercy he hath done for <hi>ours,</hi> not what's moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to <hi>vs,</hi> but what's moſt fit and commodious for both? If wee bee truely penitent for our ſinnes, and can perſwade
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21384:18"/>
our hearts of our right and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the blood and merits of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> what need we doubt of Gods Fauour?</p>
               <p>Hath he not told vs in his Word aſſur'd vs, proou'd, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated to vs, that he loues vs; yea better then we can loue our ſelues?</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Charior eſt illis homo, quàm ſibi.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Innem.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Dearer to him is Man,</l>
                  <l>Then to himſelfe he can.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And will ſuch a Cauſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any other then benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and friendly effects?</p>
               <p>Was it not in loue vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that he gaue his own Son to Vs? and can it bee but in like loue, that hee takes our Sonnes and Daughters vnto him?</p>
               <p>O thinke of it; and thinke withall, whether ſuch a loue, from Him ſo great, to Vs ſo
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21384:19"/>
baſe, be not worthy re-louing, aboue Sonnes, Daughters, Wines, Friends, Wealth, Lands, or whatſoeuer elſe the World holds moſt deare?</p>
               <p>May we not, hauing this left vs (the loue of God in Chriſt) fit vs downe as bleſſed Men and Women, with cheerefull hearts and faces, though all things elſe be torne from vs?</p>
               <p>This is the miraculous <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers Stone,</hi> that turnes any Metall it touches, into Gold.</p>
               <p>This turnes Croſſes into Comforts, Loſſes into Thrifts, Sorrows into Smiles, Wounds into Medicines, and Death it ſelfe of our ſelues, or ours, into ſuperlatiue Aduantage and Bliſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:21384:19"/>
               <head>CONSIDERATION 6.</head>
               <p>GOd may intend herein the <hi>Fathers tryall,</hi> as well as the <hi>Childs Benefit.</hi> You your ſelfe haue ſometimes giuen one of your little Ones an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and askt it againe imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately, to try his loue. So God giues vs deare Pledges, and anon requires them from vs againe, to make proofe which wee loue better, our Children or Him.<note place="margin">Chora pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Deui.</note> He allowes vs to hold them deare, but Himſelfe muſt bee dearer.</p>
               <p>Was't not inough, that God (who could haue with-held that bleſſing of marriage) gaue you ſuch a Sonne, vnleſſe hee would bargaine with you to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21384:20"/>
let him liue forty yeeres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond you? would you rather bee childleſſe, then the Father of ſuch a Sonne, as might out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runne his Father in the race of Death?</p>
               <p>If you had a iourney to goe afoote thirty Miles, will you not ſay God a mercy to him will let you ride a Dozen of it, becauſe he will not ſpare you his Horſe the other Eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene?</p>
               <p>A great Duke or Prince lends you a dainty ſweet Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, of exquiſite Workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, to delight your Eyes withall; Will you powte, and ſnuffe, and take on as iniuri'd, when after diuers yeeres vſe, he re-demaunds it from you, to bee placed againe among the Ornaments of his Gallery?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ah te, ſi flentem ſuper aethera
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21384:20"/>
mox rapuiſſet Iupiter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What could you ſay for your ſelfe; how excuſe ſuch froward bearing, if God ſhould inſtantly ſummon you to make you anſwer before him?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>CONSIDERATION 7.</head>
               <p>BVt you could haue better brookt any Croſſe, then this. But we may not chooſe our Croſſe, but beare patiently that is laid on vs. Shall wee take vpon vs to curb, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, and giue lawes to God?</p>
               <p>You deceiue your ſelfe, and lay vp but diſcomfort againſt the euill day, if you thinke no Thorne could pricke, but this. God can quickly make you
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21384:21"/>
know, that he is able to ſet a <hi>point,</hi> and <hi>ſting</hi> vpon a Croſſe of wooll.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Exod.</note> He can make a few <hi>Flies</hi> as irkeſome and intolerable, as angry <hi>Botchos</hi> and <hi>Blaynes</hi> all the body ouer. <hi>Darkeneſſe,</hi> which euery night makes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar to vs, as diſcomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and dreadfull, as inceſſant <hi>Haile-ſtormes</hi> mingled with fire, and accompanied with Thunder-ſtrokes able to ſhake the heart of a <hi>Mirmadon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Rod ſhall ſmart, which God will ſet on, though it be but of <hi>Ruſhes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A little browne paper ſhot out of an Elder-Gun, is ſcarce felt againſt the hand of a <hi>Child;</hi> The ſame browne paper out of a Musket, is able to breake the Ribs of a <hi>Giant.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:21384:21"/>
                  <l>—Quid enim mirabile, ſi quis</l>
                  <l>A lotte percuſſius, non leue vuluns habet?</l>
               </q>
               <p>What maruell if one bee in bitterneſſe, the ſtroke falling like a Talent of Lead, and the wound no light one, when the hand of God inflicts it?</p>
               <p>I know, loſſe of Children, Men of beſt <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Minds,</hi> take moſt to heart: and by the helpe of their ſharpe conceit, encreaſe and ſharpen their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction: which made that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſcape from the Pen of One, <hi>In non ſapiendo iucundiſſima vita.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sodho.</note> The ſweeteſt life is in not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wiſe. And from anothers, <hi>It's good ſometimes to be a foole.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dulce eſt deſipere in loco.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iners malorum Remedium ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantia.</hi> The more of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, the leſſe of grieuance. It's the downe-right, <hi>ſenſleſſe</hi> Remedy of Euils. For Such a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21384:22"/>
one cannot by his diſcourſe aggrauate a Loſſe.</p>
               <p>But me thinkes, Wiſdome ſhould reach vs as ſoft a Cuſhion to leane on, as Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance can: and Diſcretion forge an Armour of as good proofe againſt Aduerſity,<note place="margin">Jſocrat.</note> as Folly and Doltiſhneſſe. <hi>Qui memmit quid homo ſit, propter nullum euenientem caſum immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicè triſtabitur.</hi> He that remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers well, what Man is, (the Butt againſt which ſo many ſhafts of diſaſters are aimed euery hand-while) ſhall neuer be immoderátely hadded for any Chance obuerſant to him in this world: hee ſhall be able to ſay with <hi>Iob,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob.</note> 
                  <hi>The thing I ſcared, is fallen vpon me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If God had ſpared you from this affliction, doe you thinke you ſhould haue beene at reſt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21384:22"/>
from euils? Hath God but one Rod? Is his Storehouſe ſo vnfurniſht? Is not the very place wee liue in, a place of toyle, and turmoyle, and bicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and vexation? And ſhall we thinke to find <hi>Reſt</hi> in that, whoſe compoſition is of <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nam nemini eſſe prorſus folici, licet.</hi> No man but finds a <hi>Pound</hi> of Woe, for a <hi>Dram</hi> of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. God will not glut vs with Felicities.</p>
               <p>His manner is eftſoones to vitiate the comforts hee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes his Children with ſome vn-expected <hi>Daſh</hi> of ſorrow, leſt they ſhould imagine that true &amp; ſincere Content might be found on Earth.</p>
               <p>I haue heard you obſerue a like courſe held with your ſelfe. For, ſpeaking of ſome
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21384:23"/>
proiects of yours for a retired Country life, how much you affected the <hi>ſweetneſſe</hi> and <hi>inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency</hi> thereof, and what <hi>pleaſe</hi> you could giue your ſelfe in it: God (you ſaid) did by one meanes or other ſtill croſſe and defeate your purpoſes, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing how it might ſteale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way your heart from heauen and him, and make you deſire to moare here, and ſet vp your Reſt in the things of this world. This vſe you made of that Croſſe then; doe the like by this now. God hath taken your <hi>Darling</hi> from <hi>You,</hi> leſt he ſhould haue taken your heart from <hi>Him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:21384:23"/>
               <head>CONSIDERATION 8.</head>
               <p>POnder oft that ſaying, <hi>Sapit qui non triſtatur propter abſentia, ſed gaudet praeſentibus.</hi> He is wiſe that is not ſo much ſorry for the abſent, as ioyous in the preſent Comforts.</p>
               <p>You looke to what you haue loſt, but not to what you haue left. As God hath Croſſes moe then one: So Hee hath Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts &amp; Bleſſings moe than one. And hee hath left you a great many of them, euen <hi>Childrens Children;</hi> When others haue nor <hi>Son,</hi> nor <hi>Daughter</hi> in their inheritance.</p>
               <p>Will you, becauſe one is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued out of your ſight, way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly depriue Your ſelfe of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21384:24"/>
enioying the <hi>Remainder,</hi> as not worth thankes, now one of the tale is diminiſht?</p>
               <p>That were leke little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if you catch vp one of their Play-games, they preſently caſt away all the reſt in a fume.</p>
               <p>If in a vaſt ſuccourles <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian,</hi> or <hi>Downe,</hi> the furious Wind ſhould ſnatch off your Hat, and hurry it away beyond ouertaking, (ſo much, as with you Eye,) would you ſtraight in a Moode ſtrip off your other Garments to your ſhirt, and dare the Wind to do his worſt with thoſe Parcels alſo? O take heed of ſuch behauiour.</p>
               <p>'Tis not ſtouting, and ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, and pettiſhneſſe, but meekeneſſe, and patience, and humility, makes God <hi>propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi> What ſhall you get by ſtanding and <hi>knocking your Fiſts</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:21384:24"/>
at Him, that muſt be your one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Comfort</hi> in your <hi>Anguiſhes;</hi> or you are like to haue none at all, but <hi>ſcorne</hi> and <hi>diriſion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Set not God to Schoole; appoint him not what to take, what to leaue. He knowes beſt which <hi>Branch</hi> of the <hi>Vine</hi> to prune off.</p>
               <p>Be thankefull for them are reſerued to you, and enioy them as from a thrice friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and gracious hand. Set your loue on them as on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans <hi>Loane,</hi> which you muſt reſtore vpon demaund.</p>
               <p>Thinke not that to be your owne, that was but lent you; nor that to bee too ſoone re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired againe, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iniury might haue beene altogether kept from you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:21384:25"/>
               <head>CONSIDERATION. 9.</head>
               <p>O But, he was ſo hopefull, ſo towardly, ſo well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, ſuch a Modell of Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c. I grant you all this. But how know you, he would haue held on ſo, if he had liued longer? How many godly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue had their hearts broke with the lewdneſſe and ill proofe of their Children?<note place="margin">Tacit.</note> 
                  <hi>Eu'n many Good Princes came ſhort of</hi> Neroes <hi>firſt</hi> 5. <hi>yeeres.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What Traps doe we ſee ſet daily in the way of Vertue, to trip it, and make it fall?</p>
               <p>Occaſions to many ſinnes are preſented, and taken hold of in tract of Time, which once we neuer dreamt of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21384:25"/>
or contracting the leaſt acquaintance with them.</p>
               <p>He is gone, beginning to rel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh vertue, vntainted of vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inclinations; his ſoule had not yet dipped in the diſh of voluptuouſneſſe; wickedneſſe had not altred his heart. What hath he loſt by that? By be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Heauenly on Earth,</hi> hee is now made <hi>Glorious in Heauen.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sic fuit vtilius finiri ipſi<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>, tibi<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So was't moſt profit to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire,</l>
                  <l>Both to himſelfe, and you (his Sire.)</l>
               </q>
               <p>Beſides; you will ſay, (for paſſion hath no hoe in obiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) To you, he was ſo vſefull, ſo neceſſary, your finger next the Thumbe, growne fit to aduiſe with, to impart your Counſels to, to make a Friend and Companion of, &amp;c. <hi>Hinc
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21384:26"/>
lachrymae.</hi> This ſmoke alſo makes your eyes runne ouer. But let me tell you,</p>
               <p>To bewayle the loſſe of your Child, becauſe hee was neceſſary to you, &amp; you could ill miſſe him, is ſelfe-loue, not the loue of your Child. And to be ſad for the welfare of your Child, being euaded all perils, and highly promoted, and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified beſides; is the part of an enuious perſon, not of a Father or Kinſman.</p>
               <p>Would old <hi>Iacob,</hi> or any true-hearted Frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of <hi>Ioſephs</hi> be dreſt in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, to heare that the King of <hi>Egypt</hi> had releaſt him out of priſon, and ſent for him to Court, to make him a great Lord, and <hi>Vice-roy</hi> of the Kingdome?</p>
               <p>If you had beene told a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21384:26"/>
while agon of ſome extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary worldly preferment befalne your Sonne, aboue all that you could thinke or hope for, though in ſome farre re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote place, whereby your former familiar Conuerſes muſt be cut off; yet I ſuppoſe, that for his good, you would haue entertain'd the newes with gladneſſe, and laid by your owne particular reſpects:</p>
               <p>And now that he is exalted to the very Top and heighth of honour, and that in eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; now that he is enſtall'd a Prince among Celeſtiall Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (for not any are leſſe then Kings and Queenes that are admitted thither) will you lowre and be in dumps, as for a matter of ſpeciall diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and miſhap?</p>
               <p>Will you bee ſorry for his
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21384:27"/>
ioy? deiected for his aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? ſicke of his happineſſe?</p>
               <p>Had you rather your Sonne ſhould bee without <hi>Heauen,</hi> then you without your <hi>Sonne?</hi> This is a plaine degree of <hi>Madneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Shall wee lament for them that laugh? mourne for them that feaſt and ſing? hurt our health for them that are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly whole? Now that hee is dead and buried, nay now that his life is indeed truly <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall</hi> and <hi>Liuing;</hi> will you for his ſake goe drowne your ſelfe in your owne teares?</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Certè plus animi debet ineſſe viris.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>More wiſdome ought to reſt in them,</l>
                  <l>That weare the onely name of Men.</l>
               </q>
               <p>He hath no ſence of your ſorrowes for him, nor will
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21384:27"/>
thanke you for hurting your ſelfe, by the liberty you giue to the <hi>Rage</hi> of <hi>Nature.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>CONSIDERATION. 10.</head>
               <p>GOd hath by death freed him, not onely from the dangers and corruptions of the Age, wherein hee might haue beene ſwallowed, but from the common euils which may fall vpon his Suruiuers, greater perhaps, and neerer then we imagine. <hi>The Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Times is ſo bad, as pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments cannot be farre off.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To be ſet in ſafety before their approaches, whil'ſt the ſtorme is but a thickning, is no ſmall benefit.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:21384:28"/>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Comicus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>t. ap. Plutar.</note>
                     <hi>Si tu ſciebas illu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vitae tempus hoc</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ereptum ei quod eſt, habiturum proſperum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mors eius immatura exiſtiman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da erit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quid ſi moleſta habuiſſet multa ac triſtia?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Haec finiens mors, non te beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentior</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Illi fuit?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If you were ſure that hee ſhould haue enioy'd</l>
                  <l>The life reſt from him free, and vn-annoy'd,</l>
                  <l>Then you might thinke his death t' haue hapt too rathe;</l>
                  <l>But what if now much Ruth were to enſue,</l>
                  <l>And troublous ſtormes, which Death preuented hath,</l>
                  <l>Was't not in that, more kinde to him then You?</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>If yee lou'd mee</hi> (ſaith our Lord to his Diſciples) <hi>ye would
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21384:28"/>
verily reioyce, becauſe I goe to the Father;</hi> out of this trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and euill world.</p>
               <p>So if we lou'd our Children, and Friends departed, it would bee a more regular courſe to expreſſe it, in gratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating their eſcape by Death from ſo manifold hazards and euils of life, and their eſtating thereby into ſo ample beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and happineſſe, then in giuing ſcope to thoſe <hi>effeminate</hi> plaints, and <hi>diſtaffe</hi> lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>That which eaſeth vs of all burdens and cares; Is the end and death of our miſeries; The euerlaſting farwell to all ſmart and woes; Preuents our ſeeing, ſuffring, and doing of much euill; Cuts the Cords where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee are hampered in the world, and hindred to goe to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21384:29"/>
God; Is the accompliſhment of our ſanctification; our <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> to Glory, rendring vs into the Armes and Embrace of our Bridgroome <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> neuer more to be ſeparated, or diſioyned from him; doth it preſent vs cauſe of <hi>penſiueneſſe</hi> and <hi>mourning,</hi> or of <hi>Iubile</hi> and <hi>reioycing</hi> rather?</p>
               <p>Is the tired <hi>Bondman</hi> ſorry for the approach of night, that he may <hi>giue ouer,</hi> and goe to <hi>reſt?</hi> Is the brute <hi>Oxe</hi> grieued to be <hi>vnyoked?</hi> was euer <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riner</hi> ill apaid, that after long and doubtfull toſſing in a dreadfull high-going <hi>Sea,</hi> hee had recouered the <hi>ſafe</hi> &amp; <hi>quiet Hauen?</hi> Or <hi>baniſhed man,</hi> that hee was call'd home to his <hi>Country</hi> and <hi>Kinred?</hi> Or <hi>Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> that hee was brought out of a <hi>Dungeon,</hi> into the <hi>liberty</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:21384:29"/>
and <hi>pleaſures</hi> of a <hi>Palace?</hi> And will you ſtill weare a <hi>Cloudy brow,</hi> and wither away in your <hi>Mournings</hi> for him, that is a ſharer in all theſe <hi>Priuileges</hi> and <hi>Bleſſings?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>CONSIDERATION. 11.</head>
               <p>ELeuenthly: You remember the ſaying; <hi>Schola crucis, Schola lucis.</hi> The Schoole of Tribulation is the Schoole of Edification. The Graecian Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb is like it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Thoſe things that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vs, teach vs. You may perhaps learne more out of this Affliction, then proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty euer could teach you in all your life. This may make you looke into your Conſcience,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21384:30"/>
examine the ſtate of your ſoule, weepe your owne <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruings,</hi> and iuſtifie God in all his <hi>Doings;</hi> and in this <hi>Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular,</hi> though the waight were doubled &amp; trebled vpon you. Pray that theſe effects may be wrought in you.</p>
               <p>Theſe will proue <hi>ſalubres cogitationes, lacrymae beatae, verni imbres;</hi> holſome Meditations, Teares of Grace, Aprill ſhowres, which will cauſe the flowres of Conſolation to ſpring vp in your heart.</p>
               <p>When I loſt the better halfe of my ſelfe, (the <hi>Beſt of Wiues,</hi> ſuch a One, as euen by wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing could hardly haue beene exceeded, the Country that bred her, being left poore of ſuch another;) <hi>Pectore concepi nil niſi triſte meo:</hi> You can iudge (for your hand dropt the firſt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21384:30"/>
                  <hi>Balſome</hi> into my wound) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there were not cauſe for my <hi>Breſt</hi> to bee full fraught, burſting-ripe, with <hi>Anguiſh</hi> and <hi>Dolour?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And how long had the wound beene kept rawe, if I had wilfully inſiſted here, and ſate onely plodding, and ſhowring <hi>Teares</hi> vpon my <hi>Loſſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But when at length (almoſt too late) I turn'd away from <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>humane Reaſon,</hi> (ill aduiſing Friends in this Time and Occaſion) to Religion, and conſidered this Croſſe as the <hi>Rod of God</hi> for my many many ſinnes; That it was not a <hi>beating vpon the Coates,</hi> but laid on in good earneſt, with a prouoked angry hand; That he was conſtrained to runne this rugged Race with me;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21384:31"/>
Though my Griefe were not leſſened by this conſideration, yet it began to be turned into a righter Channell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Recenti Malo, priorum quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> admonemur.</hi> The freſh Euill which I ſuffred, laid freſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mee former Euils I had done. And where before I grieued for the ſuffring, now my griefe was to haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſo to ſuffer.</p>
               <p>Here was ſorrow changed into ſorrow; worldly ſorrow for a <hi>Precious,</hi> but Temporall <hi>Loſſe,</hi> into godly Sorrow to Repentance, neuer to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented off. <hi>Dolor ipſe iam volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas erat.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plin.</note> There was now a kinde of pleaſure in theſe <hi>bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh drops.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now began <hi>Nature</hi> to bee content to wipe her Eyes, and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that ſuggeſted the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21384:31"/>
of ſuch a <hi>Iewell,</hi> to lay her hand vpon her Mouth; and the golden Morne of Comfort to dawne to me.</p>
               <p>Now I found it true, That <hi>God will not alway be chiding, nor keepeth his anger for euer.</hi> That his correcting is not to deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but to ſaue vs from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſtroyed and condemned with the World.<note place="margin">Cypr.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee chaſtens vs, to amend vs, and amends vs, to ſaue vs.</hi> When we ſtoope, he is appeaſed. <hi>Diſcipline goes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but pardon followes after.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I willingly kiſt the Rod, that beat me neerer to Heauen and God; and bleſt the Occaſion, that led mee from ſorrow to ſorrow, that I might arriue at <hi>true</hi> and <hi>ſound</hi> Ioy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O how good was it for me to be ſo afflicted!</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. Iudg.</note> 
                  <hi>Out of the Eater came
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21384:32"/>
meate, and out of the Strong came ſweetneſſe.</hi> According to the meaſure of our ſorrow, ſo is his Conſolation.</p>
               <p>Finally, now I ſaw how groſſely paſſion had made my thoughts ouerſhoote before; not onely in wronging her happy ſoule, by ſo often wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her againe in theſe <hi>Elements of ſorrow,</hi> who walkes <hi>arme in arme</hi> with Angels; but euen in charging God fooliſhly, (par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me, O bleſſed Fountaine of long ſuffring and Goodnes) as ouer-cruell and rigorous to his Creature, (rauiſhing our Comforts from vs, then, when wee had cauſe to hold them cloſeſt to our boſome; delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſporting in our vn-reſiſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble miſeries and ill-turnes;) who indeed of <hi>very faithfulneſſe had cauſed me to be troubled.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:21384:32"/>O what a <hi>Foole,</hi> a <hi>Franticke,</hi> a <hi>wild prodigious thing is Man</hi> thus tranſported, till God vouchſafe his finger, to <hi>temper,</hi> and <hi>tune</hi> him right againe!</p>
               <p>This End the Lord in his mercy made for Mee; This was the <hi>Method</hi> of my <hi>Cure,</hi> the <hi>Crop</hi> and <hi>Harueſt</hi> of my <hi>ſowing in Teares;</hi> And my <hi>Wiſh</hi> &amp; <hi>Hope</hi> is, that by his <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> Yours may be like.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>CONSIDERATION. 12.</head>
               <p>TWelfthly. And now, Sir, ſumm vp theſe parcels, &amp; ſee if the foot of the Account declare you not a Gayner.</p>
               <p>You haue loſt a Son, whom all that knew, lou'd liuing, and commend dead. One you had
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21384:33"/>
bred vp for Heauen; and haue now return'd him to the true Owner, the <hi>Father of Spirits.</hi> Is he not well there? doe you thinke hee would bee better here? would you haue him change his glorious Eternall Manſion, for a ragged, reeling, mudwalld Houell?</p>
               <p>Did you not ayme at his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Citizen</hi> there, inſtructing, preparing, fitting him for it? Could you wiſh a righter Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be taken thither, then when the Ages viciouſneſſe, &amp; infections example had dropt leaſt ſlubber and ſoyle vpon him?</p>
               <p>Are you ſorry hee is early there arriued, his Veſſell ſafely landed before you thought he ſhould?</p>
               <p>What though (in your e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme) others were neerer
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21384:33"/>
Land then he? Is it any diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage to a Merchant, that his Ship ſo farre behind the reſt, while they lye ſtill at Anchor, is flown to ſhore fraught with welcome lading?</p>
               <p>Paines haue chas'd his ſoule out of this <hi>Houſe of Earth:</hi> But is not <hi>Abrahams boſome,</hi> where Angels haue lodg'd it, a ioyfull <hi>Receptacle?</hi> Come, waſh your Cheekes, giue no further paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage nor <hi>indulgence</hi> to your <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vina bibe, &amp; laetus veſcere pane tuo.</note> Eate your bread with gladneſſe: You thought you were hurt, and are benefited rather.</p>
               <p>He is not cleane gone,<note place="margin">Praemiſſus, non amiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</note> but onely gone before. His Morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is ended, rather then his life. You haue loſt him for a <hi>Time,</hi> God hath found him for <hi>Euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Reioyce and bleſſe God, that
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21384:34"/>
you had ſuch a Son. Had him, did I ſay? You haue him ſtill. Not one Child the fewer haue you for his taking hence.</p>
               <p>When God turned the <hi>Captiuity</hi> of <hi>Iob,</hi> the Text ſaith, hee gaue him twice ſo much Subſtance of euery kind, as he had before.</p>
               <p>He had 7000. Sheep before, now hee had 14000. Three thouſand Cammels before, now 6000. Fiue Hundred Yoke of Oxen before, now 1000. 500. Shee-Aſſes before, now 1000. of them alſo. Why were not his Children doubled as his other Bleſſings?<note place="margin">Gregor.</note> Hauing Ten Children before, why had he but Ten now? Becauſe thoſe in Heauen were his ſtill.</p>
               <p>But oh! How much chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from that themſelues were, or that their Brothers
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21384:34"/>
and Siſters are in their Fathers Houſe!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iobs</hi> Children on Earth, though the prime Women of the Land for Beauty, would appeare but <hi>Ethiopians,</hi> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the radiant gliſtering faces of Them in Glory. Their Feſtiuall Apparell here, though as rich as <hi>Salomons</hi> Royalleſt <hi>Mantles,</hi> would ſeeme no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then <hi>Cannas,</hi> or <hi>Haire-cloth,</hi> being ſet in match with the Robes of Glory, and immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, bright as the light it ſelfe, of thoſe <hi>Heauen-dwellers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as great Ods is there betweene your Immortall Son, and his Mortall Brethren and Siſters.</p>
               <p>You may, when you will, haue him preſent with you in your minde and thought. You may ſee him as he was, <hi>A yong
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21384:35"/>
Plant</hi> in your houſe; You may ſee him as he is; <hi>A bleſſed Soule</hi> in Gods heauenly Palace.</p>
               <p>Liue you mindfull of your owne Mortality, and Eternall life; and let your heart leape vp into ioy, that he hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy hit the <hi>White,</hi> whereat o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are but leuelling; And weares the <hi>Garland,</hi> for which others are doubtfully wraſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and contending.</p>
               <p>He ſits aloft, and ſmiles at this <hi>Emmet</hi>-hill of Earth, with ſuch a deale of Buſtle and Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyle, and Vanity, &amp; Foolery, and Miſchiefe, &amp; Wickednes left beneath him; Out of the Gun-ſhotte of Temptation, freed from ſinne, in ſafety from Foes, reſting from labours, exempt from ſighs, and teares, and cares; A Conſort with Angels, and happy Spirits that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21384:35"/>
ſee Gods Face, and attend vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Throne; laughing euen <hi>Kings,</hi> and all their <hi>painted</hi> Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Pleaſures here, to ſcorne.</p>
               <p>There you ſhall one day ſee him againe face to face, in that very <hi>Houſe of clay,</hi> which hee laid downe, when hee left the World and You, (though al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in Quality:) And (if that may make to the increaſe of your Bliſſe) I am perſwaded, know, and enioy him, ſee Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the richer in your Seed, his ioy augmented and made fuller by yours, and yours by his</p>
               <p>Let <hi>Sadduces</hi> deny this, and <hi>Gentiles</hi> deride it; This is the <hi>Hope of Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There you ſhall ſing that <hi>Alleluïa</hi> with him,<note place="margin">Reu.</note> to him that ſits vpon the Throne, and to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21384:36"/>
the Lambe, that hath redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med you from the earth, and made you <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> to God his Father; and to the bleſſed Spirit of Truth, and Comfort, proceeding from them both; the All-glorious, Ineffable, Eternall Trinity; To whom in the meane time, let vs in earth with them in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, (knees, faces, and hearts bending to the duſt before Him.) render all Praiſe, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Maieſty, and Dominion for euermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Soli Deo Trin-vni Gloria.</q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:21384:36"/>
               <head>FILIVS AD PARENTES.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iuo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ex Epitap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cu iuſdem nobilis Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenis Ger<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mani, qui in Angliae inter pere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>grinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit, &amp; in Eccleſia Sancti <hi>Olaui,</hi> Londini, in Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribus Crucigeris ſepultus iacet.</note> 
                  <hi>fruor tandem veris (ne flete Parentes)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Delicijs, Coelo, Poſteritate, Deo.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Deare Parents weepe not, I liue, and haue abode</l>
               <l>In Bliſſe; enioying Heauen, poſterity, and God.</l>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
